<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true patterne of pietie meete for all Christian householders to looke vpon, for the better education of their families, in the feare and seruice of almightie God. Collected out of the fountaine of holy scriptures, for the especiall vse of the faithfull in the congregation of Malpasse in Cheshire. By Iohn Parker.</title>
            <author>Parker, John, 1534-1592.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1592</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08940</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19217</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109979</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845605</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845605</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10514</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08940)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10514)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 736:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true patterne of pietie meete for all Christian householders to looke vpon, for the better education of their families, in the feare and seruice of almightie God. Collected out of the fountaine of holy scriptures, for the especiall vse of the faithfull in the congregation of Malpasse in Cheshire. By Iohn Parker.</title>
                  <author>Parker, John, 1534-1592.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 55, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By [J. Danter for?] Iohn Wolfe, and are to be solde at his shop within the Popes head Alley, in Lumbard strete,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1592.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Actual printer's name conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Print faded on title page, affecting imprint.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Devotional literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian family --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10514:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10514:1"/>
            <p>A TRVE PATTERNE OF Pietie, meete for all Chriſtian houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders to looke vpon, for the better education <hi>of their families, in the feare and</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of Almightie God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Collected out of the fountaine of holy Scriptures, for the eſpeciall vſe of the faithfull in the congregation of Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe in Cheſhire.</hi> By IOHN PARKER.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>GEN. 18.17.19.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p n="17">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>17</label> And the Lord ſaid, ſhall I hide from Abraham the thinges which I doe.</p>
               <p n="19">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>19</label> For I know him, that he will commaund his ſonnes and his houſholde after him, that they keepe the way of the Lorde, to doe righteouſnes and iudgement, that the Lord may bring vpon Abraham that he hath ſpoken vnto him.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 101.2.6.7.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p n="2">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>2</label> I will walke in the vprightnes of my heart, in the middeſt of my houſe.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>6</label> Mine eyes ſhalbe vnto the faithful of the land, that they may dwel with me. he that walketh in a perfect way, hee ſhal ſerue me.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>7</label> There ſhall no deceiptfull perſon dwell in mine houſe, hee that telleth lyes ſhall not remaine in my ſight.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ACT. 10.1.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p n="1">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>1</label> Furthermore, there was a certaine man in Caeſarea, called Cornelius: a Captaine of the band called the Italian band</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">verse </seg>2</label> A deuout man, and one that feared God with all his houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, which gaue much almes to the people, and prayſed God continually.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Iohn Wolfe, and are <hi>to be ſold at his ſhop with in the Popes head</hi> Alley in Lombardſtreete, 1592</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:10514:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10514:2"/>
            <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN and well affected Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, together with the reſt of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<hi>in the Congregation of Malpaſſe, who</hi> haue giuen their names vnto Chriſt I. P. wiſheth al holy and perfit increaſe of Gods gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, with the happie finiſhing of that good worke begun in them, euen through our Lord and Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Chriſtian brethren, my prayers to God on your behalfe are, that you may grow in all ſpiritual graces, and bee eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent faith. And if I (though vnworthie I
<pb facs="tcp:10514:3"/>confeſſe) might in ſome meaſure bee v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as Gods inſtrument and meane, for the furthering and building of you vp in that worthy worke, I ſhould ſurely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count my ſelfe greatly fauoured of the Lord. So that if I may know wherein to doe you good, (beyonde that which is done already) aſſure your ſelfe of this, that according to my poore power, I wil not faile you. And hereunto I will wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly bee led, not onely in regarde of worldly kindneſſes, and curteſies recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued lately and liberally from you, (for al the which I reſt greatly indebted) but eſpecially for the holy bond of our chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian profeſſion: whereinto, as we haue through Gods goodneſſe made ſome entrie, and in ſome ſort well begun: So I hope we ſhall holde on therein, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer bee wearie, vntill wee come to the ende of our faith and hope, euen the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of our ſoules. And becauſe I haue no better way yet to teſtifie my loue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faigned, then either by writing, or ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king: therefore: (though not as I would)
<pb facs="tcp:10514:3"/>yet as I coulde, by reaſon of my mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde infirmities and ſickneſſes, I haue diligently laboured to offer vnto your Chriſtian and curteous acceptations, a few holy rules and briefe obſeruations, for the godly and well gouering of your ſeuerall families, by Catechiſing them, and ioyning in faithfull prayers to Almightie God with them. The matter it ſelfe is collected out of the ſacred wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring of Gods holy word, and reduced into as ſhort an epitome as poſſiblie I could, for memories ſake. I haue not taken this paines, as one that would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade you to accept of this direction and none other, (knowing right well, that there are farre better ſet foorth by more learned and godly Miniſters) or for that I would tye you to one ſpeciall forme of Prayer in your Families: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the ſpirite which is in you, wil in due time teach you aboundantly to craue al things at Gods hands, according to your ſeuerall neceſſities. But my ſimple and vnfained purpoſe herein is this; that for
<pb facs="tcp:10514:4"/>as much as, that I am better acquainted with your eſtate and wants, then any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can be who knoweth you not, and that the continuall care which I haue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you for your good, can no better way be ſignified or manifeſted, than by prouoking you to well doing. I haue therefore endeauored to frame this ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle for you to looke vpon, that you hereby finding out, and conceiuing the order and manner how to glorifie God, by offering vp holy and continnall ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of praiers and praiſes vnto his maieſtie, as alſo howe to occupie your ſelues in other exerciſes of pure religion before him, might hereby in ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient time hauing learned both the matter and maner of the ſeruice of God: wholy bend your ſelues to the carefull and conſtant practiſe of all holy duties, vnto ſo mercifull a Father, moſt to his glory and your edification and comfort. And if I vnderſtande that you take that in good part, &amp; eſteeme this little work. though as a ſimple (I confeſſe) yet as a
<pb facs="tcp:10514:4"/>ſound ſignificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of my vnfeigned loue towards you, and care to doe you good: then ſhall I not onely thinke this labour (though it be not worthy of that name) well beſtowed for your ſakes, but alſo to accompliſh ſome far better thing, if my poore talent will extende thereunto for your better proceeding in that good race, whereinto you are entered. You know the poore widowes mite was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of God, not in regard of the gift, but the mind of the giuer, &amp; I hope this ſhall be no leſſe. Farwell my good bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and the Lord Ieſus be with you to confirme and inable you to euery good worke, that you may be kept blameleſſe vntil his glorious comming, &amp; ſo walke in this world in his feare, that we may in the concluſion of your pilgrimage, ende your daies in his bleſſed fauour, &amp; at the laſt, liue with him for euer. <hi>Amen,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your aſſured brother in Chriſt, yea your ſeruant for Christ his ſake to further your ſaluation.</hi> I. Parker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:10514:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:10514:5"/>
            <head>THE PREPA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiue to prayer.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Obſeruation. To ſtir vs vp to praier theſe thinges to be conſidered.</note>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Raier is a lifting vp of the hart to God, with an aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red faith to be heard, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth: <hi>Pſal. 25, 1.2. Pſal. 86.2. &amp; Pſal. 143.8.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. What prayer is, viz.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Prayer is two folde. <hi>1.</hi> either pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique <hi>2.</hi> or priuate.<note place="margin">1. How mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde proſer is viz.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1. Conc.</hi> Publique it ſhall ſuffice to reade <hi>1. King. 8.</hi> how
<hi>Salomon</hi> built a houſe of praier at <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Publique.</note> which was vſed of all the faithful many yéers after. And our Sauour in his time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueth them which abuſed the place of publique prayer. <hi>Math.</hi>
               <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> and in this reſpecte a promiſe is made to two or thrée, being gathered together in Chriſts name, in the houſe of praier <hi>Math. 18.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:10514:6"/>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2. Conc.</hi> Priuate prayer, which wée here intreate of.<note place="margin">2. Priuate</note> This is commaunded by God <hi>Pſal. 50.15.</hi> &amp; by Chriſt <hi>Math.
11.18.</hi> by the Prophets <hi>Ierm. 10.23. Ioel. 2, 32. Zecha. 12.12.13. &amp;c.</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by the Apoſtles, as appeareth: <hi>1. Theſſ. 5.17. Epheſ. 6.18: Luk. 21.36.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This priuate prayer was practiſed not only of our fathers before the law: as appeareth in
<hi>Abraham Gen. 18.18.</hi> and <hi>Gen. 24.</hi> where we read, that his very ſeruaunt could frame a praier to God, which no doubt hee had learned of his Maſter. Alſo by <hi>Iſaac. Gen.
25.21.</hi> and <hi>Iacob: Gen. 32.9.</hi> but alſo by the godly vnder the lawe: as we reade of
<hi>Moſes: Exod. 33.18. Deut. 9.20. No. 12.10, Ioſhua. 7.6.7.8. Iudg. 3.9.7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> After the law in time of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes: as appeareth, <hi>Dan. 6.10. &amp; Chap. 9. totum. Iſay. 37.15.16.17. Ier. 9.1.2, Chron. 20.18. &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>Dauid,</hi> in his Pſalmes in infinite places, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth the exerciſe of priuate prayer: profeſſing that he wil preuent the mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:10514:6"/>watch to praye, and that he will pray at morning, euening, and noone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tide: yea, ſeauen times a day, that is many times.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> This was vſed of the Apoſtles of our Sauiour: as appeareth, <hi>Actes.
2.42. &amp; 1.14. &amp; 10.2. &amp; 16, 13.</hi> and for this cauſe, both <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> and our ſauiour, gaue to their diſciples a forme of prayer: as appeareth, <hi>Luk.
11.1.2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For this cauſe, vz. In that there was no greater comfort to the faithful then to talke to God by praier.</p>
            <p>We reade the Saints haue praied in all places: as <hi>Iſaac</hi> in the fieldes,
<hi>Daniel</hi> in the Lyons denne, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles in priſon, and our Sauior Chriſt himſelfe in the mountaines and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, and others in other places as occaſion ſerued.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. We are to obſerue the neceſsitie of this dutie of praiers Viz. Rom. 12.1.</note> Regard of Gods commaund, who as he commaunded the Children of
<hi>Iſrael</hi> to offer morning and euening ſacrifice: ſo hath commaunded vs by the bleſſed Apoſtle, to offer vp our
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:10514:7"/>ſoules and bodies, as holy and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Sacrifices vnto God,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 12.1.</note> not onely in praier, but alſo in all other partes, of his holy ſeruice.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> In reſpect of Gods promiſes made to them that call vpon him: as
<hi>Pſal. 50.15. Matth. 11.28. Deut. 4.7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Becauſe of the threatnings de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt thoſe that doe not praye.
<hi>Ier. 10.23<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Pſal. 79.6.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> In reſpect of our owne dayly ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities and wants, he being the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine from whence we muſt fetch eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good and perfect gift: <hi>Iam. 1.5, 17. Iohn
3.27.</hi> and for this cauſe, that we might ſee our wantes, hee gaue vs a forme of prayer.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">4. We muſt be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>full to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> muſt pray. viz.</note>
               <hi>1.</hi> That it be in the ſpirit, that is not with carnall, but with ſpirituall hartes, our affections being lifted to heauen in ſo heauenly an action: as alſo, that it be trueth &amp; ſinceritie, not in the lips onely, or in hypocriſie to be ſeene of men.
<hi>Math. 7.5.6, 7. &amp; 15.8, 9.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> That we pray not for Gods be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:10514:7"/>to conſume them on our luſts and concupiſcences, but to imploy the ſame to Gods glorye, leaſt our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers be vnprofitable. <hi>Iam. 4.2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> That we approach before God, with a purpoſe to withſtand and reſiſt the ſinnes which we confeſſe and pray againſt, or elſe we praye in vaine. <hi>Pſal.
66.8.72. Tim. 2.19.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> In prayer, that wee be void of malice &amp; enuy, and commend the eſtate of others as well as of our ſelues vnto God, yea, to pray for our enemies, and eſpecially to be mindefull to deale ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly with the Lorde for the proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous,<note place="margin">Math. 5.23. &amp; 4.44. Pſal. 122.6, 7. 1. Tim. 2.1.</note> religious, and happie eſtate of our Prince and gouernour, both in Church, and commonwealth: yea, and although any Magiſtrate ſhould be a wicked man,<note place="margin">Prou. 27.27.</note> yet to pray for him.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, not to appoint God a time of hearing our prayers,<note place="margin">Iam. 5.8.</note> but to tary his leaſure, who ſéeth what is beſt for vs.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">5. Wee are to obſerue the end <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> prayer was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned. viz.</note>
               <hi>1.</hi> To acknowledge our obedience vnto God, &amp; the greatnes of his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:10514:8"/>from whom we receiue al things, and to talk familiarly with him as one friend with an other, alwaies prouided that we praye to none but him, &amp; that onelie in the name of Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>Ioh. 16.23. &amp; 16.23. Math. 6.9.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> To acknowledge our thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to his Maieſtie for all graces and mercies both ſpirituall and bodily: as our election, redemption, ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, his worde and Sacraments, our creation preſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, health, life, liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and peace, and all good bleſſinges whatſoeuer. <hi>Eph. 5.2.1. Pet. 1.3. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Becauſe by praier we entertaine God in our houſes, and acknowledge our ſelues to haue renounced Sathan, and to haue opened the doores of our hearts, that God may come and dwell with vs, and wee with him, as one friend with an other <hi>Reuel. 3.20.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">6. &amp; laſt thing, To prepare vs vnto praier, is to marke, the effect of praier, viz.</note>That God neuer let the praiers of his ſeuantes goe emptie and returne without a bleſſing, as was expedient for his glory and their good: as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:10514:8"/>by theſe ſcriptures. <hi>Exod. 17. Ge. 35, 5. 2. King. 19.15.2. Chr. 20, 36. Ioſh 10, 12, 13. 1. Sam. 1, 10.</hi> to <hi>16.2. Chron. 6, 18.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> To conclude, let vs remember, that if we will haue God to heare our prayers, wee muſt be ready to heare him calling vnto vs by his worde and the miniſtrie thereof, as wee would haue him to heare vs when we call, and not to turne backe our prayers.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> That if wee will haue God to heare vs,<note place="margin">Conclu. thus. Look. Prou. 1.27, 28. ad fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</note> that we be readie and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to heare the crie of our poore and needie brethren.<note place="margin">Pro. 21.13. cap. 11.17.24.25.</note>
            </p>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Next to the preparatiue, before wee come to laye downe the formes of prayer it ſelfe: this is to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of. vz.</head>
               <p>THat euerye Chriſtian who will rightlie knowe and learne how to be thus prepared &amp; to ſerue God truly, prouide by all meanes lawfull, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:10514:9"/>and purchaſe the ſacred holy Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as the beſt and principal riches he can labour for, according as God hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded in <hi>Deu.</hi> where he teacheth that not onely Princes,<note place="margin">Deut. 17.9.10.11.</note> but Subiectes muſt be acquainted with his lawes, to know their dutie, and both <hi>Dauid</hi> and Chriſt himſelfe haue ſhewed the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſednes of them that meditate in Gods lawe night and day,<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.1. &amp; 119 12. Iohn. 5.39.</note> &amp; ſearch the holy ſcriptures, wherein euerlaſting life is contained, and to moue vs hereunto, we haue worthie examples in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Church: of them that not only did labour in the ſcriptures to finde out the truth of the doctrines of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and to trie the ſpirits as <hi>Iohn</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth:<note place="margin">Acts 17 11. Iohn 1.4.</note> but alſo traind vp their children from their Cradles, in the knowledge of the ſame. And fuxther, becauſe this is the pearle, for the buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whereof, a man muſt ſell all hee hath, if his abilitie will extend ſo farre: and that it is the only fortreſſe for the afflicted conſciences.<note place="margin">Math. 13.45. Prou. 23.23.</note> Let euery man
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:10514:9"/>(though neuer ſo poore) conſtraine him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to bee honored with this Iewell, without the which hee cannot knowe God, &amp; not knowing him,<note place="margin">Rom.
10.14. ad 17.</note> can neither rightly nor truely call vppon him, but periſh in his ignorance,<note place="margin">Iam. 10.23.</note> and bee num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred amongſt the enemes of God. Therefore as thou loueſt the Lord, thy owne ſoule, and the ſoules of thy fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: delay not, deferre not, but procure &amp; prouide a Bible, aboue all thinges elſe whatſoeuer. God giue thée this grace.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>3 The Scriptures of God contained in the holy Byble being thus prouided: It is next to bee obſerued, that the word and prayer bee alwaies ioyned together. viz.</head>
               <p>At al times before we humble our ſelues to praier, to read one chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for the better ſtirring vs vp to that holy dutie: that is to ſay, Before mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning prayer, one Chapter out of the olde Teſtament, beginning at <hi>Geneſis,</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:10514:10"/>and at night, alſo before euening pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer, a Chapter out of the newe Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And if any place as wee reade ſéemeth hard vnto vs, it is good rather with reuerence to let it paſſe, then with raſhneſſe to enterpret the ſame: way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with patience till that either by ſome learned expoſitor, godly preacher, or ſome other place of ſcripture we can attain to find out the ſence of the place, alwaies hauing a care to obſerue thoſe places that ſéeme hard vnto vs till wee haue learned the true vnderſtanding of them.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Before the reading of the worde, and Cathechiſing, vſe this ſhort Prayer.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O</hi> Lord open our eyes, that we may ſée the wonderfull things and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent doctrines which are written in thy word, and may receiue comfort by thy gracious promiſes contained in the ſame. Let vs learne hereby more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitly to hate ſinne, and loue righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:10514:10"/>and graunt that wee may ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the things which wee heare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and ſo beléeue the things which we vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, and prayſing that which wee beléeue, that we may bee more &amp; more able to glorifie thy name in this world, and be fully confirmed in aſſured hope of that glorie prepared for the faithfull in the world to come, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>4 The word being thus read with reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and care, then let the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours,<note place="margin">Here ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erue that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> that wil perſwade vs, that all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſport <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Gods
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> is too much, and ſo will breed te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſnes in vs.</note> together with their whole fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, humbly fall downe on their knees, and the Maſter himſelfe, or one in his abſence, whome hee ſhall appoint to be the mouth for all, and with a true heart, inuocate vpon God as followeth.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Morning Prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Moſt glorious and bleſſed Lorde God, who art the Father of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and fountaine of all grace and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:10514:11"/>Thou Lord who haſt commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vs that in all our diſtreſſes, wee ſhould come vnto thée, and offring our prayers vnto thée with a right hart, and true faith in the name of Chriſt, haſt promiſed to heare vs, behold Lord euen before thée, who haſt thus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded and promiſed, we ſinfull and vnrighteous creatures doe humble our ſelues at this time, both in our ſoules and bodies: beſéeching thy excellent Maieſtie to looke from heauen with thy mercifull fauour vppon vs, accepting our praiers, which we ſhall powre out before thée, and directing vs ſo to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the ſame vnto thy holineſſe, that thou mayeſt accept them in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</p>
               <p>We confeſſe O Lord God of heauen that we are moſt vnworthie to appeare before thee, and more vnworthie to obtaine any fauour at thy gratious hands, in regarde of the infinite &amp; hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous offences which we haue commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt the puritie and excellent
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:10514:11"/>vertue of thy lawes which condemne vs in our ſinnes, and reuealed vnto vs our rebellion and vnthankfulnes. For O Lord wee haue a lawe in our mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, reſiſting and fighting againſt the law of our mindes, whereby through the infirmitie and vanitie of the fleſhe: we finde in our ſelues no pronenes to that which is good, nor any courage to reſiſt the thinges which are euill: and this our vntowardneſſe is ſo much the greater, by howe much the more wee violate thy will and tranſgreſſe thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly precepts, not onely in ignorance, but alſo in knowledge, and many times a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt knowledge, both gréeuouſly and fearefully: ſo that thy authoritie on the one ſide, nor thy mercies on the other, haue neither moued, nor allured vs to obey or ſerue thée, as we ought to haue doone, and theſe our ſinnes which are ſufficient to condemne vs, go not alone but haue too many companions: for O Lord our infidelitie, impaciencie, hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of heart, abuſe of thy patience, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:10514:12"/>of thy worde, and little profiting by it, are erdinarie ſins into the which we fal daily, wee being ſuch by nature, as eſtéeme more of our owne pleaſures and profites then of thy glorious &amp; bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſeruice: our harts as corrupt foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines yéelding foorth nothing but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt of thy prouidence, hypocriſie, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſnes, carnall and worldly concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcences, and neglect of all good duties towwards thée and all men: the fleſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually rebelling againſt the ſpirite, ſo that O Lorde if thou ſhouldeſt haue dealt with vs according to iuſtice, wée had all periſhed in theſe our ſinnes and ignorances before this preſent, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore obteining this fauour to come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thée, we vnfeignedly confeſſe that againſt thée O Lord, euen againſt thée alone we haue committed theſe ſinnes and wickedneſſes, beſéeching thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie to pardon our ignorance &amp; blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that we cannot ſee them more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and confeſſe them more penitentlye then now we doe, wherein wee muſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:10514:12"/>néedes acknowledge our ſinnes to bee the greater, by how much the leſſe our repentaunce appeareth to bee at this houre. Yet foraſmuch as that O Lorde God thou haſt reuealed thy ſelfe in thy word, to be God of infinite mercy and goodnes, to them that truely repent &amp; come vnto thée, in the name of Chriſt Ieſus. Wee are hereby imbouldned to humble our ſelues before thy Maieſtie, beſeeching thee for Chriſt his ſake to touch our harts with vnfained ſorrow and true contricion, for all theſe, &amp; all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our ſinnes, &amp; graunt we may both ſo ſée and abhorre our guiltines and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines, that wee may obtaine mercie &amp; forgiuenes through his precious death and paſſion: which we beſéeche thee to accept, as a ful ſatiſfaction for the ſame wiping them all out of thy booke of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce, that they may neuer be laid to our charge, nor riſe vp in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt vs. Giue vs a lyuelie and true faith, to lay holde on theſe thy mercies promiſes vnto vs in him, that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:10514:13"/>wée may be able to reſiſt all the fierie darts of the deuill. And as wee craue this grace for that which is paſt, ſo let it pleaſe thée of thy Fatherly mercie, to aſſiſt &amp; ſtrengthen vs in the reſidue of our life, to performe and accompliſh all that obedience which thy Maieſtie requireth of vs, and as thou art our Father, ſo regarde vs as thy children, and ſend down the power of thy Spirit into our hearts, that wée conſidering how thou ſitteſt in the heauens, and ſearcheſt the ſecrets of all mens hearts, may haue continuall care to ſet our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections on thinges which are aboue, and not on thinges which are beneath: but if that thy wiſdome, power, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, mercie and trueth, or whatſoeuer elſe thy Maieſtie is knowen by, may be truely reuerenced and honored of vs, ſo that all prophaneſſe of hart, all worldlyneſſe, and fleſhly ſecuritie may be farre remoued from vs.</p>
               <p>To this end O Lorde vouchſafe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs that ordinarie &amp; happie meanes
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:10514:13"/>of the faithfull and ſincere preaching of thy bleſſed worde, that thy ſpirit wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king therewith, it may effect in vs all good graces both of faith &amp; repentance: Yea, we beſéech thée ſende foorth faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full labourers amongſt vs, and bleſſe thoſe whome thou doeſt ſend, with all graces neceſſarie, both puritie of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine and ſinceritie of life, and ſo ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie them, in al their ſtudies and labors, that by their miniſterie and example wee may increaſe in all true zeale and loue to thée and thy worde, and may haue iuſt cauſe to embrace them déerly in our hearts, and accompt reuerently of them, as of thy mercifull inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ſent vnto vs for our great good. Graunt O Lorde that we maye not be hearers but dooers of thy will, and that the like mind may be in vs, that was in Chriſt Ieſus, and in all our godly forefathers, euen with al willingnes and readines, yea, to make it our meate and drinke to do thy will. And for aſmuch as Sathan is a continuall aduerſarie, ſéeking to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:10514:14"/>choake the ſéede of thy worde, and all other good graces in vs: therefore O Lorde let it pleaſe thée, to take vs vnto thy ſelfe: ſo that no temptation of the worlde, fleſh, or diuell, ouertake vs: but deliuer vs from ſinne, and all the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of ſinne.</p>
               <p>O Lorde giue vs grace to ſtoppe ſin at the beginning, before it come either into action or conſent, ſo that wée ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming at thy glorye in all our labour and affaires, and walking as in thy preſence. Endeuouring alwayes to kéep a good conſcience, both in thought, worde, and déede, towards thy Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie and all men, all thy good bleſſings maye followe and fall vpon vs, to the great ioye of our heartes, and glory of thy name, through Chriſt Ieſus. And for theſe our bodies, wée onely craue bread for the day, &amp; true contentation with that thou ſendſt, crauing thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vpon vs in our labours, that wée may bee able to miniſter to our owne neceſſities, and rather be helpfull then
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:10514:14"/>chargeable to others, and alwayes to reſt as well contented with aduerſitie, as proſperitie, hauing aſſurance that al ſhall fall out for the beſt, to them that loue and feare thée: aboue all thinges kéepe vs from vſing vnlawfull meanes to liue by, and let vs be ready to ſupplie the wants of our brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as we would haue them to fulfill our neceſſities. O Lorde forgiue our enemies, and turne their harts if it be thy will, and graunt wee may alwayes bee more readie to take then giue offence to any: wee are this day to walke before, O Lorde goe before vs, and ſo preſerue vs from ſinne and the daunger thereof, that at night we come before thée againe to giue thée thankes for theſe and all thy mercies in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
               <p>Thou Lorde as dutie bindeth, and as thou haſt commaunded, wee pray thée remember thy Church vniuerſall, and more perticularly this Church of England. Send thy worde frée paſſage throughout the worlde, and graunt a
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:10514:15"/>good gouernment to be continued ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall, Lord ſanctifie the hartes of all thy people that enioye it, &amp; graunt wée may walke worthie of it in our liues and conuerſation: bring to nought all their councels that are enemies vnto it and enuie the proſperous paſſage ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; of; preſerue our gracious Prince, the honorable Counſell, the godly &amp; faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full biſhops and paſtors of thy Church and all that feare thy name, &amp; further or fauour thy trueth: defend vs from our enemies, and goe forth with our armies againſt them: comfort the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with all true comforts, &amp; turne their ſorowe into ioye. Haue mercie vpon vs and al thy people euery wher, eſpectallye in this land. Bleſſe this whole familie with all graces neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for our callings euen for Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſake, in whoſe name for theſe and all other the teſtimonies of thy fouour, we praye as he hath taught vs in his holy Goſpell, ſaying: <hi>Our Father which art in heauen, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:10514:15"/>
                  <head>A ſhorte forme of Morning prayer, to be vſed when want of opportunitie and vrgent affaires doe hinder vs to vſe the other.</head>
                  <p>O Lord our God before whoſe pure and holy eyes, no vncleanes or ſin can be hid or couered, we wretched &amp; ſinfull creatures, and yet by thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie thy vnworthie and poore ſeruants, do humble our ſelues before thée, in the name of Ieſus Chriſt, acknowledging our ſelues to haue grieuouſly ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thée, in thought, word, and déed, from our firſt enteraunee into this world, vnto this preſent time, and our repentaunce for the ſame we confeſſe, hath béene very little or nothing at all, ſo that wée may iuſtly feare and bluſh to approch into thy preſence, with ſo ſmall contricion of hearte, and wound of conſcience, as we now doe, but that wée knowe thy mercie excéedeth thy wrath, in which mercie we beſéech thée to looke downe from heauen vpon vs,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:10514:16"/>for Chriſt Ieſus ſake, and ſo to worke repentaunce in vs, for our vnthankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, abuſe of thy patience, ignorance, infidelitie, neglecte of thy worde, and all other our ſinnes, as our worldlines, carnall ſecuritie, and the reſt, that it may pleaſe thée to accept vs in the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of thy Sonne, and to accompt of the ſame as a perfit raunſome for vs, aſſuring our Spirits by the teſtimonie of thy Spirite, that our ſinnes are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, and wee reconciled to thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie through thy promiſed mercie in him. And to that ende that the time to come may be better employed then the time paſt: therefore let it pleaſe thée to giue ſtrength vnto vs, that we may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt all ſinne, and the temptations ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and conſume our dayes in continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all care to performe all good duties vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy maieſtie, both in body and ſoule. And as this day wee are to walke in this worlde among ſundrie and great enemies of the ſoule, ſo derect vs by thy grace, that we may be circumſpect in al
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:10514:16"/>our thoughts, wordes and workes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeming the ſeaſon, becauſe the dayes are euill. O Lord giue vs grace in all our labours, and enterpriſes, princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally to ayme at thy glorie, preferring the ſame before our owne pleaſure and profite, and ſuffer vs not to ſtart aſide from the obedience of thy wil in any of our affaires, but giue vs grace ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and in vprightnes of heart, to walke before thée, as becommeth the Saintes and children of God, ſo that all propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, vanitie, euill ſpeaking, anger, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, impaciencie, couetouſnes, and all other corruptions of our nature maye vaniſh and die, and wee by thy grace, and the power of thy holy ſpirite, may be made more then Conquerours ouer them in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
                  <p>O Lord graunt that al our labours taken in hand, according to thy will, may haue ſuch iſſue and effect as may be for thy glorie, the good of thy Church and our owne comfort, and becauſe all good graces are wrought in vs by the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:10514:17"/>miniſtrie of thy worde, O Lord vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe this thy bleſſed ordinaunce vnto vs, let vs hunger after it, as after our appointed foode, and in the light there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, let vs walke as Children of light, and glorifie thy name more and more, in the pure and true obedience thereof, in all vnfained loue to thy Maieſtie, and all our brethren for thy ſake. Bleſſe this whole familie, and graunt that the gouernours may rule with wiſdome and godly diſcretion, and thoſe that are gouerned may obey as thoſe that are called by thy word, and ſanctified by thy ſpirite, ſo that we may all glorifie thée, and in the end be glorified of thée.</p>
                  <p>Saue thy whole Church we beſéech thée, this Church of England eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, beſéeching thy good Maieſtie not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſcatter the teſtimonies of thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and grace vpon thy people euery where, but eſpecially vpon theſe our dominions, and euery parte thereof. Regarde aboue the reſt, the good and proſperous eſtate of our Soueraigne
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:10514:17"/>Lady Quéene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> honoring her Royall perſon, with all graces neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for her worthie and high calling, &amp; poſſeſſe her hart with a principall zeale for thy glory, ſo that by her holy go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement, ſinne and ſuperſtition may be beaten downe, and all vertue and godlines erected and maintained to the further increaſe of thy kingdome, and ouerthrow of Sathans dominions.</p>
                  <p>Bleſſe the honorable counſellers with wiſedome and holy Iudgement, that from their heades and heartes, as from a happie fountaine may flowe all good direction and orders for the ſound and right gouernment both of Church and commonwealth. Bleſſe all thy mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and Church guides, with all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of graces fit for their places, and increaſe the number of thoſe that bee faithfull, whome thou wilt vſe to adde ſoules to thy kingdome, and roote out thoſe that are vnfit and not able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the charge which thy word lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vpon them.</p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:10514:18"/>
                  <p>O Lorde, thou that art Lorde of the Harueſt, ſend faithfull laborers into the Harueſt, in all places wée beſéeche thée. Bleſſe all inferiour Magiſtrates with all graces fitte for their places. Bleſſe this whole land, and all ſortes of people in the ſame, with the gift and grace of true repentance, both for the preuenting of thy iudgements threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, &amp; for the remouing of thoſe which are vpon vs. Fight for vs againſt our aduerſaries, and through thy mercie let vs obtaine at all times victorie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them, that thou maieſt ſtill bee our God and we thy people, and thy name may be great in <hi>Iſraell.</hi> Confound An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt and all thine enemies, comforte and in thy good time deliuer all thy poore priſoners that are in affliction and bands for thy trueths ſake, and arme vs againſt the like trials: be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifull to all thy people and giue peace and conſolation of conſcience to them that want it. Theſe and all good graces for our ſelues and al thy people where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:10514:18"/>we pray as our Sauiour Chriſt hath taught vs, ſaying.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Our Father which art in Heauen, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>5 At dinner time, this muſt bee obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that if there be any childe or ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant which can reade in the houſe: that the Maſter cauſe him to reade a Chap. in time of dinner,<note place="margin">The like is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to bee done at ſupper time.</note> or els if hee be able when he hath dyned, to reade one himſelfe before he riſe from ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, which will helpe well to ſeaſon the meate, if the thinges that be read be rightly meditated of, alwayes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, that we giue thankes both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and after meate.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">SIXTLY. Heere note that Euening pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er be done ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per or ſhortly after, becauſe otherwiſe, the fleſh will be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e to praye, but of the two, the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</note>O Lorde God moſt mightie, our lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing &amp; mercifull Father in Chriſt Ieſus we humble our ſelues before the throne of thy Maieſtie, humbly craue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing pardon for all the ſinnes which this day or any time of our life hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we haue committed againſt thée, beſéeching thée to forgiue our coldnes
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:10514:19"/>in thy ſeruice, our vnthankefulnes for thy mercies, and ſo to mollifie our hard and barren heartes, with the force of thy worde, and operation of thy bleſſed Spirite, that we may more truely and effectually both ſée and repent vs of all our ſinnes heretofore committed. Yea, graunt déere Father, that we may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and hate ſinne in all men, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in our ſelues, and be affraide to bee ſtained and defiled with the corruption thereof, though it be but in appearance. And becauſe wée finde in our ſelues a willingnes to do good (which commeth of thy grace) and yet haue no power to performe the ſame: therefore wée pray thée O Lorde reforme this our nature, and make it more apt to the obedience of thy will, ſo that all ſinne wherewith we haue ſtained thy holy Image in vs, may be remoued out of our hartes, and decreaſed, and the graces of thy ſpirit increaſed in vs as thou knoweſt them néedfull for vs.</p>
               <p>O Lord we are pilgrims here, hide
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:10514:19"/>not thy commaundements from vs, ſet the feare of thy Maieſtie before our eyes, let vs ſéeke with all our hartes to ſet foorth thy prayſes by a holy &amp; righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conuerſation, as thou haſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, being alwayes afraid to vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late or breake the leaſt of thy comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, kéepe vs ſafe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and manners of the worldly, and make vs a light of veritie and holynes vnto this peruerſe and crooked genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion amongſt whome we liue, giue vs grace good Lorde to walke worthie of our high calling in Chriſt Ieſus, in all true zeale for thy glory, and vnfaigned loue to thy Church, and graunt that in all our ſtudies and labours, our care may be ſuch to pleaſe thée, as that wée may haue the ioy of thy Spirit, and the happie peace of conſcience to dwel con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually in our hartes. To this end let thy worde be the lanterne to guide all our ſteps by, and to direct vs to all our doings, and grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t we may ſhew foorth the fruites thereof, in all vertue and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:10514:20"/>godlynes.</p>
               <p>With fauor regarde our labors and enterpriſes, which this day wée haue trauelled in or hereafter ſhall proſecute according to thy wil: &amp; graunt we may ſo vſe this world, as though we vſed it not, and in all thinges and aboue all thinges, let thy glory and the ſetting forth of thy prayſes, be moſt deare vnto vs at all times.</p>
               <p>Bleſſe thy Church euery where, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peciallie here amongſt vs in this land: giue all true zeale vnto our Prince, to gither, with a princely and wiſe heart: giue vnto her Counſellers the ſpirit of wiſedome and counſell: vnto our Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges the ſpirit of iudgement: and to all our Magiſtrates the ſpirit of courage and godlines, to puniſh vice and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vertue: giue wiſedome and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes to our paſtors and teachers and all holy obedience to all thy people: miniſter all néedefull comfortes to the afflicted: giue thy worde a frée paſſage, and graunt all thinges néedefull for the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:10514:20"/>finiſhing of the number of thy elect peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, euen for Chriſt Ieſus ſake.</p>
               <p>Therefore Lorde we thanke thée for all thy mercies, and for this mercifull libertie wée inioye to come before thée. Wee render from the bottome of our heartes all vnfained prayſes vnto thy Maieſtie for our creation and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all preſeruation: for our health, life, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie and peace, for our foode, rayment and all other thy benefites, for the good of our bodies. But eſpeciallie wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe our ſelues infinitelie bounden for thoſe bleſſings which are greater, as our election before all worldes, our redemption by Chriſt Ieſus, our voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and calling by the goſpel, our ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification by the Spirit, for calling vs out of darkenes, into thy meruellous light, and for ſeperating vs in ſuche poore meaſure, from the loue of this worlde, and worldly commoditie. We praiſe thée for thy worde, for thy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, and all thy vndeſerued mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, not only vppon our ſelues, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:10514:21"/>vpon our Prince and countrey: wée thanke thée for her gratious Maieſtie, and the peace we enioy vnder her: wée thanke thée for the wiſe, and honorable Counſellors, the godly Maieſtrates, faithfull Miniſters, &amp; for all thy faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full people. Lorde continue ſtill merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto vs, in Chriſt Ieſus. Confirme vs in the Faith and obedience of thy Sonne, as many as thou haſt alreadie called: and call all thoſe that goe aſtray, and hauing finiſhed thy worke: come ſpéedely in the cloudes for our full deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance we pray thée, yea come Lorde Ieſus, come quickly.</p>
               <p>Now Lord we commend our ſelues, our ſoules and bodies into thy good handes, beſéeching thée to kéep and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue vs this night, to giue quiet reſt and ſléepe to our bodies, and peace of conſcience to our ſoules, that we being preſerued from daungers and reſtored to the vſe of thy fauor: the next day we may be careful to performe all good du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to thy Maieſtie, moſt to thy glorye
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:10514:21"/>and our comfortes in Chriſt Ieſus. In whoſe name for the continuance of thy fauor, in graunting all theſe and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good graces: we praye as he hath taught vs, ſaying.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our father wich art in heauen halow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed be thy name, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>7 Certaine petitions to be vſed in mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or euening prayer, as occaſion ſhall ſerue.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>In time of any generall viſitation, as warre, ſickenes, famine, &amp;c. <hi>Say this petition.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>O Lorde our God, thou dooſt iuſtly correcte vs for our ſinnes by this thy hand: make it profitable vnto vs wée beſéech thée, and afflict not our land aboue meaſure, leaſt the enemie ſay, where is their God become? Wee are thy people &amp; the workemanſhip of thy handes: remember therfore thy aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent mercies to our forefathers,
<hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Iſaac, Iaacob,</hi> and for Chriſts ſake
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:10514:22"/>ſuffer not our enemies to preuaile ouer vs, but put an ende to our miſeries, that we may liue and dwell in peace, and inioy our former libertie, to ſerue thée, and the fruites of the earth in due time. Let vs therfore ſée the ſinnes that moſt diſpleaſe thée, and repent truely of them, that ſo thou mayeſt turne thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable countenance towardes vs, in our Lorde and Sauiour Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>In any particular viſitation of thy ſelfe or anie of thy familie, ſay this peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</head>
                  <p>O Lorde our God, thou art righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in all thy dooings, but wee are moſte vnrighteous, open our eyes to ſée our ſinnes which thus diſpleaſe thée, and touch our hartes with vnfaig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſorrow for the ſame, that we may no longer prouoke thy diſpleaſure. And good Lorde graunt that we may ſée thy purpoſe in thus afflicting vs, that wée may finde out the cauſe, and repent vs
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:10514:22"/>of it, lay no more vpon this thy ſeruant then he is able to beare, let not the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie haue power ouer him, but aſſiſt him with thy ſpirit, againſt all aſſaults whatſoeuer, graunt him patience, and deliuerance out of this miſerie in thy good time, which way ſhal ſéeme beſt to thy Maieſtie. Theſe and all good gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, wee craue for Chriſt Ieſus ſake, our onely Lorde and Sauiour, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>8 Note, That the night ſeaſon muſt not bee ſpent in idle and filthie talking, which becommeth not Chriſtians, but ſhall be giuen accompt of. See <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſ. 5, 4. Math.
12.36.</hi> Therfore foure nightes in the weeke, let them bee ſpent in honeſt and vertuous confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, that tendeth to edification, in reading Gods worde, in ſinging of Pſalmes, as theſe ſcriptures com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde: vz. <hi>Epheſ. 4.29. Colloſſ. 4.6. Epheſ. 5.19. Colloſſians. 3.16.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The other 2. nights let them bee paſſed away as oportunitie and health ſhall
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:10514:23"/>permit, in conferring with our family and examining them in foure or fiue queſtions of theſe principles of Faith, which followe: as the ſcriptures com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund and exhort vs: vz. <hi>Deu. 6.6.7.8.9. Eccle. 12.1. Dan. 12.3. 2. Tim. 3.14.15. He. 5.12. 1. Pet. 3.15.</hi> which Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures I pray you look ouer with aduiſe.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ The Lords day muſt thus bee ſpent, vz.</head>
                  <p>IN hearing the worde, and ioyning with the Congregation in praier and thankeſgiuing. In receauing the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments when occaſion ſhal ſerue. In viſiting the ſicke, reléeuing the poore, meditating on Gods worde and his workes, auoyding all lewd companie, as alſo carding, dycing, &amp;c. &amp; at night to follow the example of the Church of
<hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea,</hi> in calling to minde the things wee haue learned as theſe ſcriptures teach vs,
<hi>1. Iohn 4.1.1. Th. 5.21. Act. 17.11.</hi> And in thus dooing the peace of God ſhall be vpon you.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:10514:23"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>A breefe Cathechiſme</hi> Conteining the principles of the Chriſtian faith, meete to bee learned of all true Chriſtian Families.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IS there any creature in heauen or in earth, which muſt not be ſubiect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aunſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.1. &amp; 1.27. &amp; 2.7. Exod. 20.2. Ioſhua. 24.14.15.24. Rom
11.36. 1. Tim. 6.15. Apoc. 19.16.</note> for he hath created both Angels and men, and all other creatures both in Heauen and earth, and all places, to that ende, that they ſhoulde ſerue and obey him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How is this ſeruice and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence performed?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> When we reuerence his word and kéepe his commaundements,<note place="margin">Luk. 12.47.48. &amp; 17.9.10.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thereby wee manyfeſt both our ſubiection and his authoritie ouer vs, as our Lorde, and the God of power to require the ſame of vs.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:10514:24"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> What call you the worde of God, or which are his commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I call that the worde of God which is contained in ſacred and holye Scriptures,<note place="margin">Iohn. 5.39. Heb. 2.2, 3.4. Luke 16.29.31. Deut. 4.13. Exo.
19.18.20.</note> of the olde and new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, commonly called the Byble, and thoſe are his commaundements which he gaue in <hi>Mount Sinay,</hi> which are as it were an abridgement and ſumme of the whole ſcriptures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How many commaundements be there?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Ten.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Rehearſe them?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Then God ſpake all theſe wordes &amp;c.<note place="margin">Exod. 20.1. ad.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How can theſe ſilly and dumbe creatures bſerue Gods woorde and Commaundements? for you ſay that al creatures muſt obey him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In continuing in that firſt order and eſtate wherein the Lord firſt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced them,<note place="margin">Pſal. 148.5.6. Pſal. 104.9.</note> and whereto by his word hee firſt enioyned them.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:10514:24"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Howe is man inferiour to the vnreaſonable creatures in this obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In that our firſt Parentes ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing broken Gods Commandements,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.6.16.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Rom. 5.14, 15, ad 20.</note> in eating of the forbidden trée, they themſelues became not onelye ſinfull and accurſed,<note place="margin">Gal. 3, 22. Pſal.
14.1, 3.</note> but haue left vnto vs who doe ſuccéede them, the inheritance of their ſinne which wee call originall ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What then ſhall wee thinke of our ſelues that are thus corrupted?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Surely that by nature we are the children of diſobedience &amp; wrath,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.1, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 3. Ro. 7.19.20, 23</note> prone to that which is euill, and vntoward to that which is good, for this originall ſinne hath ſo infected both ſoule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, that we can doe nothing but tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe Gods lawes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Que.</hi> What call you tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Tranſgreſſion is the breathe of the Lawe,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.7. Deut. 5.21.</note> which the Apoſtle calleth ſinne.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:10514:25"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Doth God allow of this ſinne, or may we think our ſelues not to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny whit the worſe, or leſſe bleſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are ſinfull?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> God forbid we ſhould ſo thinke, for as we ſinne and breake Gods laws dayly in thought,<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.12. Gen. 6.5. Eccleſ. 7.22. 1. Iohn. 1.8. Math. 5.19.22. Rom. 6.23. Gal. 3.10. Iam. 2.10.</note> word, and déede: ſo by the iuſtice of God, we deſerue eternall death bothe of ſoule and bodye for the leaſt of our ſinnes, though it bee but in thought and in all our life, as the due and deſerued ſtipend thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> This being ſo that wee by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture can doe nothing, and ſinne deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing death: what are wee to doe for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie in this caſe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We are herein principally to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue foure things, without the which our eſtate is but miſerable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> I pray you rehearſe them vnto me, that I maye diſcerne whether you know them or no.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt<note place="margin">Rom. 7.7.9.10.11.</note> I am to praye to God to open my eyes that I may beholde my ſelfe, and ſée how I am conuicted of my
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:10514:25"/>ſinne by his lawe, and haue incurred his wrath againſt me for the ſame.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>(2)</hi> I am to repent and to forſake this my ſinne,<note place="margin">2. Act.
3.19. Ioell. 2.12.13. Ier. 3.14.15.22.</note> which hath brought vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon me this condemnation and miſery.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>(3)</hi> I muſt vppon this repentance, ſéeke onely for remedy in Chriſt Ieſus,<note place="margin">3. Iohn. 3.16. Math. 11.28. 1. Iohn 2.1. Epheſ. 2.9. Act. 4.12. Gall.
2.21.</note> and not truſt to any good workes or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruings of my owne:</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>(4)</hi> And laſtly, I muſt haue aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of faith, &amp; be ſtedfaſtly perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that Ieſus Chriſte by his holy ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferinges,<note place="margin">4. Heb.
11.6. Iam. 1.6. Gall. 3.13. Iohn 14.18.26.27. Rom. 8.15. Heb. 4.16.</note> hath appeaſed the wrath of his father, hath eaſed me of the burthen of my ſinnes, and will not onely quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken me by his comforting ſpirit: but reſtore me hereby from death vnto life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How hath Ieſus Chriſt thus effected our peace and deliuerance fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo great puniſhment?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe as hee was man,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.30. 1. Tim. 1.15. Eſay.
53.5. 1. Pet. 2.24. Rom. 4.25. Colloſſ. 1.19.20. &amp; 2.15.</note> hee ſuffred for ſinne in that nature in the which it was committed, vz. in mens nature: and ſo ſatiſfied Gods iuſtice by that one oblation of his owne body and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:10514:26"/>blood for our attonement: ſecondly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, he was able to ouercome and breake the bonds of death, and ſo who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and fully to effect my ſaluation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Hauing thus eſcaped the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and curſſe of death, tell me more plainely howe thou attaineſt euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Chriſte Ieſus hauing accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed perfect righteouſnes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 32.2. Iohn 14.16, 17. Iohn 17.13, 21, 22, 23, 24.</note> it is mine by imputation: and being ſanctified by the fulnes of his ſpirite which hee hath receiued, hee doth offer and preſent vs to the father, crauing that wee may be partakers of euerlaſting life and glorie with him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Shall all be pertakers of this life and glorie?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 1.12. &amp; 3.18. Iohn 20.8. Gal. 3.11. Habak. 2.4. Rom.
1.17. Heb. 10.10.38.</note> Noe, not anye but the true and faithfull belieuers, who can applye Chriſts death to themſelues, by a liuely faith, the ſumme of which faith is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Apoſtles Créede,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Rehearſe the Creede?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. I belieue in God &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:10514:26"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What call you Faith?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is the gifte of God,<note place="margin">Iohn 6.29. 1. Iohn 3.23. 1. Iohn 5.12,
13</note> and as the hand of the ſoule, to laye holde on Chriſt and his merites, and all good things which are offered and promiſed in him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How may we attaine to this Faith?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt,<note place="margin">1. Iohn 2.20. &amp; 3.24. &amp; 4.13.</note> by the inwarde meanes which God hath appoynted to worke the ſame in vs: &amp; ſecondly, by the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, ordained for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the outward meanes ordained?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The preaching of the word and miniſtration of the goſpell,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.14 Gal 4.19. Epheſ. 4.11. &amp; 1. Theſ. 5.19.20.</note> which if we neglect to receiue and practiſe, we ſhall be void of all ſaith, and ſo conſequently of all ſaluation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Hath GOD appointed anie meanes to confirme this faith?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes, the bleſſed Sacramentes,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.17.</note> of our Lord and Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How many Sacramentes be there.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:10514:27"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Two, Baptiſme, and the Lordes Supper, as appeareth, <hi>Rom. 4.11. 1. Cor. 10.2,
3. Act. 2.26. Math. 21.25. &amp; 28.19, &amp; 26.26.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What is a Sacrament?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> An outward and holy ſigne, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined by God himſelfe, and by the confirmatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the word applyed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, repreſenteth ſpirituall and inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible graces vnto vs, to manifeſt Gods fauour towards vs, and to confirme our Faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What call you Baptiſme, and what benefite haue you by it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Baptiſme is the ſeale of my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation &amp; vniting to Chriſt,<note place="margin">Rom. 4.6. Acts 22.16. 1. Pet. 3.21. Colloſſ. 2, 11. Tit. 3.5.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as before I was a bond-ſlaue to fathan And it aſſureth me, that as my bodie is wached with water, ſo by the death of Chriſt my ſoule is waſhed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinne in his bloud, and from the guilte and puniſhment of ſinne. And to conclude, it teacheth me that by Chriſtes death I ſhould learne to dye vnto ſinne, and by his reſurrection, ariſe to holynes
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:10514:27"/>oflife, which is the newe birth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What are you to obſerue in the Lordes Supper, and what dooth it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent vnto vs?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It aſſureth me by the operation of the ſpirit,<note place="margin">Luke
22.19.22. Iohn 6.53.54.55.56. &amp; 58.</note> that nowe being receaued by Baptiſme into Gods family, I ſhall be nouriſhed with the liuing bread and water of the bodye and bloud of Chriſte, as my bodye is refreſhed with the outwarde vſe of bread and wine, and that as ſurely as the bread is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and the wine is powred out, ſo aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly the body of Chriſt was broken, and his bloud ſhed for my ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How may a man knowe whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he haue this faith, which is begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the worde, and confirmed by the Sacraments?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The principall and chiefeſt ſigne thereof, is the ſpirit of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.9.10.11.14.15.16.</note> which is the ſeale and pledge of our adoption, and the earneſt penny of our Saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and this ſpirit is in none effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly but in Gods elect.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:10514:28"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How ſhall wee decerne, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this ſpirit be in vs, or no?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By the fruits thereof,<note place="margin">Matth. 3.11.</note> which will burſt forth as a flame of fire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Which be thoſe fruites?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They be theſe. Firſt, loue<note n="a" place="margin">Math. 22.37. Mark. 12.29. Exod. 20.2. Deut. 6.2.</note> to the Lord and his worde, worſhipping him in ſoule and bodye, and<note n="b" place="margin">Iob 13.15. Iohn 14.15.</note> depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vpon his prouidence both in proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie and aduerſitie: Secondly, a full<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 8.10. Luke 1.75. &amp; 10.4.2.</note> alteration in my ſelf: that I am dead to ſinne, and the maners of the world, and that I am now giuen to delight in Gods word and the hearing of it,<note n="d" place="margin">Heb. 3.12. 1. Theſ. 5.14. Coloſſ. 3.16. Iam. 5.20.</note> to exhorte others vnto well doing, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally<note n="e" place="margin">Ioſh. 20.15. Pſalm. 101. Epheſ. 6 4.</note> thoſe that are vnder my charge, being<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 8.8. &amp; 116.12. Rom.
12.1. Pſal. 50.14.15. 1. Theſ. 5.16.</note> thankefull to God for all his mercies in Chriſt Ieſus, vſing all exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes of Chriſtianitie, which tend to a godly and new life,<note n="g" place="margin">Math 6.2. 1. Cor 13.3.</note> hauing charitie towardes all men, and expreſſing the ſame by ſome ſignes of my loue, and to conclude holding faſt the holy<note n="h" place="margin">Heb. 25. Epheſ. 2.20.11.22.</note> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, with the reſt of the members whereof Chriſt is the head.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:10514:28"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How are theſe graces of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit obtained.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Euen by the ſame meanes that the ſpirit it ſelfe is obtained, which is, by faithfull prayer vnto God only, that he will not harden our heartes, &amp; cauſe vs to erre, but giue the pledge of his ſpirit vnto vs, &amp; the graces therof. <hi>vide. Pſal. 51.10, 11. Iſai. 63.17. Pſal. 50.25.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Muſt wee praye for nothing but for our faith and the ſpirit?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes,<note place="margin">Act. a. 24.29. Epheſ. 6.18.19. 1. Tim. 2.12.</note> we muſt praye not onely for our ſelues, but alſo for the whole Church: eſpeciallye hauing a care to aſke thoſe thinges at Gods handes, which may moſt ſet foorth his glory, as we are taught in the Lords prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Rehearſe the Lordes prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. Our father which art in, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> How way we be aſſured, that God will giue an aunſwere to our prayer?<note place="margin">Iohn 16.23. 1. Iohn. 2.1. 1. Pet. 25. Mark. 11.24. Luke. 11.9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, if we aſke the thinges we néede, in and for Chriſts ſake. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, if we aſke in faith.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:10514:29"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What ſay you then to the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the wicked.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They are vndoubtedly abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to the Lorde,<note place="margin">Prou. 1.28.29.30. &amp; 28.9.</note> not onely in reſpect that they want faith, but alſo becauſe they perfourme not obedience to the Lordes voyce when hee calleth, but turne their eares from it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Rehearſe now the ſumme of all that thou haſt learned?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The ſumme of all is this.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1</hi> That I finde my ſelfe to be moſt miſerable, in reſpect of Gods lawe, which condemneth me in my ſinne: In that it requireth I ſhould loue God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all, and my neighbour as my ſelfe, and yet I violate the ſame, both in thought, worde, and déede.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> That through Gods vnſpeake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able fauour, I finde remedy for my ſin, that although y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde hath giuen ſuch a lawe as I cannot performe and kéep, becauſe no other lawe then ſuch a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect rule of righteouſneſſe would agrée with his nature, therefore not by my
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:10514:29"/>owne deſeruing, but by the mercie of our Lord God in the death of his Son, and our Sauiour, the guiltines of my ſinnes taken away, and I am diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3</hi> And laſtly, that I reſt thankefull all my life long, for this exceeding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite, and ſhewe foorth the fruites of my redemption, by a righteous and holy conuerſation, ſpringing from a liuely and true faith, which is begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by his worde, and ſealed by his Spirite. This is the ſumme.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:10514:30"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Carde for Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants</hi> to looke vpon, before they preſume to come to the Lordes Table, fit to be learned of all that will not receiue vnworthelye.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>HOw many thinges are to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded and learned of them that approche to the Lordes Table, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the holye miſterie of his holye Supper.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Principally one thing, which is to examine themſelues before they eate, leaſt not diſcerning the Lordes bodye, they eate and drinke vnworthely, and ſo the bread and wine be vnto them of no greater force then the ſupper was to Judas, euen a ſeale of their condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> What meane you by diſcerning the Lordes Supper?</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:10514:30"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I meane that we muſt not come to the Lordes Table as to a common feaſt or banquet, regarding onely the outward elements, as though bread and wine were become our ſpirituall nouriſhment, but that by the outward ſignes wee be ledde as it were by the hand to that which they ſignifie, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: that Chriſt Jeſus hath ſuffered the death of the croſſe, to take away my ſinnes which are the cauſe of my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, and to bring me vnto euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life through that fulnes of grace which reſteth in him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> You ſay the principall thing to be regarded, is to examine our ſelues: wherein dooth this examination con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſte?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In theſe foure pointes eſpecially which are not lightly to be conſidered off.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Which be they, tell me briefely?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. 1.</hi> That I haue ſome knowledge to diſcerne the Lords body as is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaide, and be able by a liuely and true
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:10514:31"/>ſaith, to apply Chriſt and all his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites to my ſoule for my conſolation &amp; comfort, leaſt otherwiſe by hauing no féeling of Gods mercie &amp; loue towards me, the Sacrament doe appeare to be but a dead letter vnto me.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> That I finde my ſelfe inwardly and truely grieued for all my ſinnes both leſſer and greater, yea for all my idle wordes and vnprofitable workes, and for all ſinnes whatſoeuer, whether actuall, or originall: and that I purpoſe not to ſinne againe for any pleaſure or proſite whatſoeuer; but to behaue my ſelfe before him all the dayes of my life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in performance of all holy duties accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his worde.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> That as I ſée by the breaking or cutting of the bread, and powring out the wine, that Chriſts bodie and bloud was deuided, broken, and powred out for my ſinne: ſo to finde my heart lyf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vp vnto God, and prepared to giue humble and heauenly thankes vnto him, as for all his mercies, ſo eſpecially
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:10514:31"/>for thoſe preſent benefites which we ſée before our eyes, and pertake at his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Table. And to conclude, to bee as ready to be broken &amp; ſlaine for Chriſts ſake, as he was for mine, by taking vp his croſſe and following him.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> And laſtly, as I finde by the vewe of all theſe mercies, that God loueth me vndeſeruedly, ſo that I finde and féele my ſelfe readie to loue all men in like ſorte, though they deſerue it not, yea my very enemies,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> Are theſe ſufficient rules to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine our ſelues by?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Theſe being conceaued in our heads, imprinted in our heartes, and expreſſed in our lyues, will further our worthie receiuing, to our euerlaſting comforte.</p>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Certaine formes of Thankeſgiuing.</head>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>Grace before meate.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O</hi> Gracious and bleſſed Lorde God who giueſt al things abound ant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:10514:32"/>to thy ſeruants, and féedeſt them in due ſeaſon: we humbly beſéeche thée to ſanctifie theſe thy good creatures proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for vs, forgiuing our ſinnes, which haue deſerued the contrary. Vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing for Chriſts ſake, to giue vs a ſober and moderate vſe of thy creatures, ſo that whatſoeuer ſtrength wée receiue from them, we may beſtowe the ſame in thy ſeruice, to the ſetting foorth of thy glory in thy onely Sonne our Lord and bleſſed Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>Grace after meate.</head>
                  <p>WE thanke thy Maieſtie moſt mercifull and heauenly Father for theſe, and all thy mercies vpon our ſelues and all thy people, beſeeching thée of thy Fatherlye goodneſſe, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue thy fauour vppon vs, and vpon thy whole Church. To ſend thy word into all places, and to graunt a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall increaſe of the faithfull diſpoſers thereof. To bleſſe our Prince and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, to be mercifull to all our ſinnes.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:10514:32"/>Comforte all the afflicted members of Chriſt: arme vs againſt the day of try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. Shorten theſe dayes of ſinne, and increaſe our faith euermore. Graunt theſe and all good graces, euen for Chriſt Ieſus ſake, to whome with thée and the holy ſpirite, be al honour, praiſe and glory for euer, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>A thankeſgiuing, to be vſed <hi>after Cathechiſing.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>WE magnifie thy name O Lorde our God, for thy patience and vſe of thy word, at this and al other times, beſéeching thy Maieſtie to pardon our vnreuerent handling of the ſame, and to write in our heartes the thinges which wee haue learned, and giue vs the practiſe thereof in our liues. Lorde continue thy fauour ſtill towardes vs, by giuing a long &amp; proſperous reigne to our gratious Soueraigne, that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her godly and peaceable gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment we may ſtill enioye this libertie to thy glory, and our comfortes, both now and for euer. Amen.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
